U.S. Emergency Board No. 94 Records 5038
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board No. 94 Records
1951
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board
5038
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Transcripts and exhibits, Emergency Board No. 94, 1951: Air Line Pilots Association, International, vs. American Airlines, Inc., 1938-1951.
3113982
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 24, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Executive order of the President dated January 13, 1951, resulted in the appointment of an emergency board composed of Mr. David L. Cole, labor consultant of Paterson, N.J., as Chairman; Hon. Frank P. Douglass, former Chaiman of the national Mediation Board of Pine, Colorado; and Mr. Aaron Horvitz, Attorney of New York, N. Y.
Public hearings were begun in Washington, D.C. on January 25, l95l, and on January 29 the proceedings were moved to New York City. These hearings continued until April 27, 1951, and at the conclusion of the hearings.: the board met jointly with the parties, also separately, in an effort to secure a settlement of the disputes by mutual agreement but without success. The record consists of 4,770 pares of testimony and argument and 106 exhibits. Extension of tine to May 28, 195l, for report of the board was approved by the President. The report was made on May 25, 1951.
The complicated issues in dispute had been the subject of continuous negotiation and mediation, lasting almost 18 months, and had resulted in the taking of a strike vote. A major issue resulted from the REQUest of the Air Line Pilots Association to place limitations on the number of miles pilots would be required to fly each month, depending upon the speed of the the plane; other changes of rate formulae for pilots and copilots were in dispute, a total of 27 issues as broken down in the board's report.
In its report, the board recommended a sizeable increase for copilots, which will acerage $1,800 per year. The board did not recommend reduction in flying hours below what they now are. The board recommended increased vacation allowance for captains, a provision guaranteeing more free time for all pilots, a minimum-pay guarantee, improved sick leave, furlough allowance for poilots whith two ore more years' seniority, and increased meal allowances. Other recommendations included a no-strike clause to be made part of the new agreement and that machinery be established for submitting unsettled grievances over dismissals and interpretation of the contract to a form of arbitration.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States -- Sources; Cole, David L. (David Lawrence), 1902-1978.; United States. Emergency Board No. 94.; Air Line Pilots Association; American Airlines.
3113982
- Report to President by Emergency Boards - May 25, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Report to the President by the Emergency Board - May 25, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 5, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 6, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Transcript of the Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 9, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 10, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 11, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 12, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 27, 1951 (No. 94) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Company Exhibits 1-29: Presidential Emergency Board No. 94 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Record Group DA 94 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Amendment to Agreement between American Airlines and the Air Line Pilots (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Final Argument and Summation of the Air Line Pilots Association International before American Airlines Presidential Emergency Board (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Routes Flown by a Chicago Based Pilot (1930-50) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Development of United States Transport Type Aircraft from 1930 to the Present Time (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Turbine Jet and Turbine Jet Powered Propeller Air Line Aircraft (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The Aircraft Under Design (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Crew and Passenger Increase with the Development of Transport Type Aircraft (Box 2, Folder 7)
- The Development of Transport Aircraft on American Airlines from 1930-51 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- American Airlines Output, Pilot Productivity and Earnings (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Growth of Output per Pilot Crew: New York-Chicago Run (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Larger, Faster and More Complex Aircraft and High Altitude Flying has Multiplied the Weather Problems of Air Line Pilots (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Evolution of the Cockpit of Commercial Aircraft as Related to Instrumentation and Flight Crew Performance (Box 2, Folder 12)
- The Increase in Numbers and Complexity of Aeronautical Radio Navigation and Communication Facilities (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Comparison of Terminal Area Problems: 1945 and 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- A Comparison of the Approach and Landing Operation of Past and Present Air Line Aircraft (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Effects of Altitude and Pressurization on Pilot Workload (Box 2, Folder 16)
- CAA Airway Aids and Navigational Facilities Over AA Routes (Box 2, Folder 17)
- The Pilot is the Proving Ground for New Equipment (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Background and History of the Origin, Development, Purpose and Duties of the Air Line Copilot Status (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Laws, Past and Present, Affecting Airline Pilots' Rates of Compensation, Rules and Conditions of Employment (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Civil Aeronautics Act and National Defense (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Decisions of the Civil Aeronautics Board Indicating the Special Treatment Given to Air Carriers on the Basis of National Defense (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Technological Unemployment of Pilots on American Airlines (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Effect of Airline Retooling on Pilot Employment (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The DC-6B (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Pilot Seniority Lists Indicate Adverse Effect of New Equipment on Pilot Roster (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Chronology of First Pilot Pay on American Airlines (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Background, Application, and Explanation of the American Airlines Pilots' Mileage Increase Determination Proposal (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Reducing Hours Without Reducing Take Home Pay (Box 2, Folder 29)
- American Airlines Crew Cost Related to Output, Revenue, Expense, and Profitability (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "Many Called: Few Chosen" (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Promotional Prospects of American Airlines' Copilots (Box 2, Folder 32)
- History of the Copilot Pay Issue (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Inequities of Present American Airlines Copilot Pay Scale (Box 2, Folder 34)
- The American Airlines Copilot Pay Proposal (Box 2, Folder 35)
- There are No Regulations Governing on Duty Hours of Air Line Pilots (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Analysis of Pilot Working Conditions on American Airlines (Box 2, Folder 37)
- An Explanation of the American Airlines Pilots On-Duty Hour Proposal (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Minimum Pay - Irregular Flying (Box 2, Folder 39)
- The Deadhead Pay Proposal of American Airline Pilots (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Reserve Pilot - Minimum Guarantee (Box 2, Folder 41)
- First Pilots Monthly Guarantee (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Hours of Duty (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Deadheading (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Minimum Guarantees (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Furlough Allowances (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Furlough Pay (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Landing Pay (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Training Pay (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Expenses Away From Home (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Sick Leave Requirements of Flight Personnel (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Vacation Periods and Vacation Pay Allowances of American Airlines Pilots (Box 2, Folder 52)
- The Present AA Agreement Does not Contain a Provision Relating to the Establishment of Rules, Working Conditions, etc. (Box 2, Folder 53)
- The Agreement Between American Airlines and the Air Line Pilots Association (Box 2, Folder 54)
- American Airlines, Inc. - Pilot Hours Ramp to Ramp (1946 and 1950) (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Pilot Headcount - Payroll (Midmonth), 1946 and 1950 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Statement of the Air Transport Association with Respect to the Examiner's Report and Findings (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Aircraft Speeds Established in Currently Effective Employment Agreements Between ALPA and the Major Air Lines (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Pilot Utilization American Airlines (1946-50) (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Publicity and Advertising of American Airlines Inc. Reflect Equipment Trends and Performance (Box 2, Folder 60)
- The DC-6B (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - January 25, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - January 26, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - January 29, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - January 30, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - January 31, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 1, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 12, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 13, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 14, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 15, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 16, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 19, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 26, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 27, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - February 28, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 1, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 2, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 12, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 13, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 14, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 15. 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 16, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 20, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 21, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 22, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - March 23, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 2, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 3, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Transcript of Proceedings of the Emergency Board - April 4, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 29)